<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="245">Thomas Merton's Journal, #10, "The Red Diary" [a machine-readable transcription]</title>
            <author>Thomas Merton </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University General Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno> </idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Available at the Emory University through the Beck Center.</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1996</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Merton Journals</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">
               <l/>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title> </title>
                  <author/>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher/>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine/>
                  </address>
                  <date/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <seriesStmt>
                  <title/>
               </seriesStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note anchored="yes"/>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date>1653</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>May 1, 1996</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name/>
               <resp/>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Edited to parse against TEILite DTD.</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date/>
            <respStmt>
               <name>OCR scanning and proof-reading by Hamilton Carroll; Tagged by
Chuck Spornick</name>
               <resp>Beck Center, Emory
University</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Entity references
included.</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 type="Preface">
            <head>
               <hi rend="Bold">Thomas Merton's Journal #10,&quot;The Red
Diary&quot;</hi>
            </head>
            <head>
               <hi>Foreword</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The following pages are a typed
facsimile transcription of Thomas Merton's holographic journal
designated #10,&quot;The Red Diary,&quot;in the Thomas Merton Studies
Center Collection at Bellarmine College,Louisville, Kentucky. In
addition to the facsimile, the transcribers have appended notes,
English translations from the Greek, Latin and French, an index, a
bibliography of confirmed sources used by Merton, and a page-by-page
synopsis of the complete journal. </p>
            <p>The original journal is a red-leather, day-by-day calendar
journal for 1959 and thus has received its title, The Red Diary.  Of
the possible 365 pages for entries, Merton used only 63: his first
entry appears on page 4, designated for January 3, 1959;the final
entry is on page 66, designated for March 4, 1959. The remaining pages
of the calendar diary are blank.</p>
            <p>The Red Diary was obviously dated 1959 in the Thomas Merton Studies
Center Collection, but there is ample evidence to prove that not all,
and perhaps not any, of the entries were made by Merton in 1959. Page X
(43) bears the date November, 1964.Page X (50) bears the date January
31, 1965, Merton's fiftieth birthday. An interrelated portion of the
journal [pp. X(45-66)],entitled by Merton an&quot;Office for Hermits,
was begun after November, 1964 and either completed or abandoned in
early1965. It is difficult, though admittedly not impossible, to
assume that, during a six year period, Merton would have filled only
63pages in the diary. And since all the journal's entries are
similar,what can be described as an anthology or <hi>florilegium</hi>
of favorite passages from Merton's <hi>lectio</hi> 
               <hi>divina</hi>,
the entries in the journal are assumed to be more accurately
dated1964-65 than 1959. Given this assumption, Merton saves or
finds unused a red-leather diary for 1959 which becomes another journal
in the mid-sixties.</p>
            <p> Although no personal journal entries by Merton appear in this
diary it is a collection of the words of others The Red Diary reveals
Merton intimately. The Red Diary is a convergence of Merton's
spontaneous attractions. The quotations exhibit Merton's instinct for
the essential and the luminous in his reading. And by what he selects
to save Merton reveals his own interior climate. The journal section
entitled an Office for Hermits is especially significant. Here Merton
looks forward to his living at his hermitage full time and thus arms
himself with a word from his monastic fathers, both Latin and Greek, and
from the Scriptures, especially the prophetic and wisdom books. These
collected&quot;words&quot; reflect his fears and his hopes, and more
importantly they reflect his prayer, at this new and long awaited
juncture in his life.</p>
            <p>This transcription is a collaboration of friends. Dr. Erasmo
Leiva-Merikakis Professor of Comparative Literature and on the faculty
of the St. Ignatius Institute of the University of San Francisco,
transcribed and translated the Greek, French, and Latin sections of
the journal.  Jonathan Montaldo transcribed the remaining sections and
is responsible for the addenda to the text.</p>
            <p>The transcription of Thomas Merton's&quot;Red Diary&quot; was
completed under the direction of Dr. Robert E. Daggy, Director of
Research for the Thomas Merton Legacy Trust and the Director of the
Thomas Merton Center at Bellarmine College. This transcription and its
addenda are the property of Bellarmine College. All rights to the use
of this transcription are reserved by the provisions of the Thomas
Merton Legacy Trust and by Bellarmine College.</p>
            <p>Erasmo Leiva-Merikakis,San Francisco, California Jonathan
Montaldo,Collingswood, New Jersey January 31, 1989</p>
         </div1>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 n="X(5)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (5)</head>
            <lg>
               <l>O Lord and Master of my life, give me</l>
               <l>not a spirit of sloth, of despondency, of lust or</l>
               <l>of vain talking; but bestow on me thy</l>
               <l>servant a spirit of chastity, of humility,</l>
               <l>of patience and love. You, O Lord and</l>
               <l>King, grant to me to see my own errors</l>
               <l>&amp; not to judge my brother, for blessed</l>
               <l>art thou unto ages of ages.</l>
            </lg>
            <note anchored="yes">(Popular in C<hi>19 </hi>Russia)</note>
            <bibl>St. Ephrem</bibl>
            <p>All the essence of Xtianity is contained in this prayer.</p>
            <bibl>Dostoievsky.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(6)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (6)</head>
            <lg>
               <l>The one who is offended can forgive; the</l>
               <l>offender never forgives; from his crime sprouts</l>
               <l>hatred. A Christian can be a serf but</l>
               <l> must not be a slave-owner.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>Khomiakov </bibl>
            <p>Christianity does not touch but
illuminates.</p>
            <bibl> I. Aksakov.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(7)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (7)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Few men are Johnsons; yet how many men  at this
day are assailed by incessant  demands on their mental powers which
only  a productiveness like his could suitably supply!  There is a
demand for reckless originality  of thought &amp; a sparkling
plausibility of  agreement which he would have despised even if he
could have displayed; a demand for crude theory &amp; unsound
philosophy rather than none at all.</q>
            <bibl>Newman.</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">What must be the toil of those whose intellects are to be flaunted
daily before the public in full dress, &amp; underdress ever new &amp;
varied, &amp; spun, like the silkworm's, out of themselves.
<note anchored="yes">Merton identified with John Henry Newman. Of Newman Merton wrote
elsewhere: &quot;There are people one meets in books or in life whom
one does not merely observe, meet, or know.  A deep resonance of one's
entire being is immediately set up with the entire being of the other
(<hi>Cor ad cor loquitur</hi>)--heart speaks to heart in the wholeness
of the language of music; true friendship is a kind of
singing.&quot;:<hi>Conjectures of A Guilty Bystander</hi>. (New York:
Image Books, 1968), p. 188.</note> 
            </q>
            <bibl>Newman.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(8)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (8) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Let meekness, simplicity, condescension to
those lower than yourselves, condescension which would put you on an
equal level with the lowest among them, let quietness in humiliation,
patience which no offence could overwhelm, let all this become your
mind as it was of Christ Jesus.</q>
            <bibl>Met.[tropolitan] Filaret</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(9)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (9)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified">As fellow workers of the loving Christ's Spirit,
the holy men of God bear, by the grace of Christ, human sinful
weaknesses &amp; humiliations as if they were themselves liable to
spiritual foolishness. According to such heroism of faith &amp; love,
the grace of God does not abandon men who freely give themselves to
these dishonoring weaknesses &amp; silliness, but meekly &amp;
patiently He brings them to the path of Truth. Ordinary men pass
gradually from their childish mind into the life of sane intelligence
because these others, in their gracious love offer themselves to the
hard death of frank madness in the eyes of men. Such is the mystery
&amp; significance of foolishness for Christ's sake.</q>
            <bibl>A. M. Bukharev.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(10)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (10)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified">The heavenly Father uttered His hypostatic or personal Word &amp;
all came into being; but uttering His thought &amp; His will about the
existence of creation, He, at the same time, was determining for His
own personal Word or Son to take upon him the burden of all - already
foreseen - sinful disorders of the world. God the Word was mightily
creating according to the thought of His Father but already He was
dooming Himself to the immeasurable self-sacrifice in order to keep
this new created world in the meaning &amp; designation given to it --
even in spite of the foreseen infidelity of the world to its meaning
&amp; designation.</q>
            <bibl>A. M. Bukharev (on Job)</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(11)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (11) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">As for the secular world for the sake of which Bukharev left his
monastery, it did not hear his voice &amp; did not realize that he was
suffering in order to redeem &amp; to unite with Christ the secular
art &amp; thought so often suspected by the clergy as an enemy.</q>
            <bibl>Govodetzky.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(12)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (12) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Christ suffers and is crucified in the world because the sacrifice
of Golgatha is still repeated in the world until he comes. The Lord in
His glorified manhood is sitting at the right hand of the Father, but
in the earthly manhood of which He is the new Adam, in His Body the
Church, which is still in the state of Christ militant, Christ dwells
not only in His glorification but in His kenosis also.</q>
            <bibl>Boulgakov</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(13)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (13) </head>
            <bibl>
               <hi>HERACLITUS</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">Aion is a child at play, playing
draughts; the Kingship is a child's. -- Fr 52I sought for myself. Fr
101 His opinions were in general that all things are composed from
fire &amp; into this they are resolved;Everything comes to be through
fate and existing things are connected through this turning in
opposite directions.All things are full of souls &amp; daimons...He
called conflict a sacred disease and seeing, being deceived.</q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(14)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (14)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified"> They say that when asked why he was silent, he replied -&quot;That
you may babble.</q>
            <q direct="unspecified">Do not be in a hurry to unwind to the center stick the roll of
Heraclitus the Ephesian; the path is hard indeed to traverse. There is
gloom and unrelieved darkness; but if an initiate leads you it shines
more brightly than the shining sun.</q>
            <q direct="unspecified">Those who speak with sense
must rely on what is common to all, as a city must rely on its law...
<note anchored="yes">  (nb. common remains unknown to most)</note>
            </q>
            <q direct="unspecified">The divine
law has as much power as it wishes &amp; is sufficient for all / is
still left over.</q>
            <bibl>(Diog.[enes]) Frag 114</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(15)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (15)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Therefore it is necessary to follow the common: but although the
logos is common the many live as though they had a private
understanding.  Fr. 2</q>
            <q direct="unspecified">To god all things are beautiful &amp; good and just; but men have
supposed some things to be unjust, others just.  Fr 102</q>
            <q direct="unspecified">The up &amp; the down is one and the same. Fr 60.
The beginning &amp; end of a circle are common. (70.b)  (Fr 103)</q>
            <bibl>Heraklitus</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(16)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (16) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Celui qui cherche et trouve l'Esprit du Christ en agissant bien,
celui[-]la progresse beaucoup plus s&ucirc;rement que celui [qui] ne vaque
qu'&aacute; la seule pri&egrave;re: oui, celui qui atteint le Christ dans
l'action et celui qui l'atteint dans la pri&egrave;re son souvent comme celui
qui l'atteint en r&eacute;alit&eacute; et celui qui l'atteint en d&eacute;sir.
<note anchored="yes">Whoever seeks and finds the Spirit of Christ through right
action makes much surer progress than whoever dedicates himself solely
to prayer: indeed, the person who attains to Christ through action and
the person who attains to him through prayer are often like one who
attains to him in reality and one who attains to him in
desire.</note>
            </q>
            <bibl>B1. Peter Favre, S.J. (1)</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(17)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (17)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Nous serons merveilleusement encourag&eacute;s si nous nous rappelons
souvent et serieusement que nous sommes mandates aupr&egrave;s du prochain,
non seulement par le Sup&eacute;rieur mais par le Christ lui-m&ecirc;me.  <note anchored="yes">We
would derive wonderful encouragement from remembering, often and
seriously, that we have received our mission toward our neighbor not
only from our Superior but from Christ himself.</note>
            </q>
            <bibl>St. Peter Canisius [S.J.]</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(18)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (18) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">L'Eternel semble tenir a cela en nous par quoi nous differons de
Lui.Durables, nous lui serions peut[-]etre comme les pierres nous
sont: indifferents.    Lanza del VastoIls ne sauront jamais ce qutest
la Beaute, ceux qui la cherchent a leur aise et la prennent pour un
plaisir de plus .Lanza del Vasto</q>
            <note anchored="yes">[The Eternal [God] seems to be especially keen on that part of
us that makes us different from Himself. If we had permanence, we
would probably be toward him what the stones are toward us:
indifferent.][What Beauty is will never be known by those who search
for it on their own comfortable terms and take it to be but one more
pleasure.]</note>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(19)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (19) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">When a man finds it is his destiny to suffer he will have to accept
suffering as His Task, his single and unique task. He will have to
acknowledge the fact that even in suffering he is unique &amp; alone
in the universe. No one can relieve him of his suffering or suffer in
his stead. His unique opportunity lies in the way in which he bears
his burden.</q>
            <bibl>V. Frankl.  <hi>From Death Camp to
Existentialism</hi>p. 78 Boston: Beacon Press, 1959.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(20)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY. </docAuthor>
            <head>X (20) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">There is also purpose in that life which is
almost barren of both creation and enjoyment &amp; which admits of but
one possibility of high moral behavior, namely in man's attitude to
his existence.</q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X (21)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY</docAuthor>
            <head>X(21)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified">BLANK</q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X (22)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X(22)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified"> In the presence of Rabbi Hanina one went to the praying desk to
say the prayer. He said&quot;God, thou great, strong, terrible,
mighty, feared, powerful, real &amp; adorable.  He waited until the
other had finished &amp; then said to him:&quot;Have you ended with
the praise of your God? What is the meaning of all this? It is as if
one were to praise a king of this world who has millions of pieces of
gold for having one piece of silver.</q>
            <note anchored="yes"> quoted in Scholem. Main
Trends in Jewish Mysticism p. 60</note>
            <bibl>Scholem, Gershom
G. <hi>Major Trends in Jewish Mysticism</hi>. New York: Schocken
Books, Inc.., 1946.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(23)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (23) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">La personnalite n'est pas seulement une chance [chose?] fragile a
favoriser ou a defendre: [elle] est le mystere le plus profond de
l'univers ontologique.  <note anchored="yes">[The personality is not only a fragile
thing [?] to be either fostered or forbidden: it is the deepest
mystery of the ontological universe.]</note>
            </q>
            <bibl>H. Bars
Maritain en Notre Temps</bibl>
            <bibl>Bars, Henry. <hi>Maritain en Notre Temps</hi>. Paris: Editions
Bernard Grasset, 1959.</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">Une philosophie qui n'est pas antique est tout de suite vieille.</q>
            <note anchored="yes">[A philosophy which is not ancient is immediately old.]</note>
            <bibl>J. Maritain</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(24)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (24) </head>
            <bibl>Chuang Tzu. V. 1.2 </bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">The true men of old did not reject
the views of the few; they did not seek to accomplish their ends like
heroes, they did not lay plans to attain those ends. Being such,
though they might [make] mistakes, yet they had no occasion for
repentance ; though they might succede [sic], they had no
complacency...So it was that by their knowledge they ascended to &amp;
reached the Tao.</q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(25)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (25) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">The true men of old knew nothing of the love of life &amp; the
hatred of death...They accepted their life &amp; rejoiced in it, they
forgot all fear of death...Thus there was in them what is called the
<hi>want of any</hi> 
               <hi>mind to resist the Tao</hi> &amp; <hi>of all
attempts </hi>
               <hi>by means of the human to assist the</hi>
               <hi>Heavenly</hi>.</q>
            <bibl>Chuang Tzu  V1. 2.</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">Their minds were free from all thought, their demeanor was still &amp; unmoved ...They did in regard to all things what was suitable &amp; no one could know how far their action would go.</q>
            <bibl>V. 1. 3.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(26)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (26) </head>
            <bibl>Chuang Tzu</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">He who tries to share his joys with others
is not a sagely man; he who manifests affection is not benevolent; he
who observes times &amp; seasons is not a man of wisdom; he to whom
profit &amp; injury are not the same is not a superior man...V1.3.When
the springs are dried up the fishes collect together on the land. Then
that they should moisten one another there by the damp about them...it
were better for them to forget one another in the rivers &amp;
lakes. V1. 5. </q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(27)" type="Preface">
            <head>X (27) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">The Tao is a thing which accompanies all other
things &amp; meets them, which is present when they are overthrown
&amp; when they obtain their completion. Its name is Tranquillity amid
all disturbances, meaning that such disturbances lead to its
perfection.</q>
            <bibl>Chuang Tzu V1. 8.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(28)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (28) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Fishes forget one another in the rivers and lakes, men forget one
another in the acts of the Tao.</q>
            <bibl> Chuang Tzu V1. 11.</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">When one rests in what has been arranged &amp; puts away all
thought of the transformation, he is in unity with the mysterious
heaven. </q>
            <bibl>Chuang Tzu V1. 12</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes"> In the light of these and the preceding Merton selections from
Chuang Tzu, this: Reading Chuang Tzu, I wonder seriously if the wisest
answer (on the human level, apart from the answer of faith) is not
beyond both ethics and politics. It is a hidden answer, it defies
analysis and cannot be embodied in a program. Ethics and politics, of
course: but only in passing, only as a &quot;night's lodging.&quot; There is
a time for action, a time for &quot;commitment,&quot; but never for total
involvement in the intricacies  of a movement. There is a moment of
innocence and <hi>kairos</hi>, when action makes a great deal of
sense. But who can recognize such moments? Not he who is debauched by
a series of programs. And when all action has become absurd, shall one
continue to act simply because once, a long time ago, it made a great
deal of sense? As if one were always getting somewhere? There is a
time to listen, in the active life as everywhere else, and the better
part of action is waiting, not knowing what next, and not having a
glib answer.<hi>Conjectures of A Guilty Bystander</hi>, p. 173.</note>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(29)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (29) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">O Wisdom, gone away, gone, gone to the other shore, landed on the
other shore Suatra!</q>
            <bibl>Prajnaparamita Sutra</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">Le secret de nos coeurs est une seule vierge que ni l'imagination
du reveur ni le penser du penseur ne deflore ... Le secret du coeur
c'est ce pour quoi Dieu stest cachea ses creatures et ce pour quoi il
s'en rapproche.</q>
            <note anchored="yes"> [The secret of our hearts is a solitary virgin
which neither the dreamer's imagination nor the thinker's thoughts
succeed in deflowering ... The secret of the heart is that for which
God has hidden himself from his creatures and that for which he comes
close to them.]</note>
            <bibl>Haleqsee Giulio Basetti-Sani OFM. Mohammed et St. Francois p 268 n 35</bibl>
            <bibl>Basetti-Sani, Giulio. <hi>Mohammed et Saint
Francois</hi>. Ottawa: Commissariat De Terre-Sainte, 1959.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(30)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (30) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified"> Silence &amp; longsuffering are the most perfect acts that a man
may have. For it is by this silence &amp; patience that he lives and,
if he wants to speak, or if he wants to let others speak through him,
it makes him mortal. If he really wants to live, he should always
remain silent &amp; suffer God alone to speak, for what God utters is
life.</q>
            <bibl>The Book of the Poor in Spirit p 131</bibl>
            <bibl/>
            <bibl>A Friend of God (14th Century). <hi>The Book of the Poor
in Spirit</hi>. Edited by C.F. Kelley. New York: Harper Brothers,
1954.</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(31)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (31) </head>
            <bibl>Chuang Tzu.  XVIII 1.</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">Perfect enjoyment is to be
without enjoyment; the highest praise is to be without praise. .Heaven
does nothing &amp; thence comes its security; Earth does nothing &amp;
thence comes its rest. By the union of these two inactivities all
things are produced.... All things in their variety come from this
inaction. id.</q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(32)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (32) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">La saintete est douloureuse, tant qu'elle n'estpas de tous. </q>
            <bibl>O. Clement</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">Every reverse is a pointer to some spiritual truth that we were in
danger of forgetting. You therefore should strive calmly to settle
down &amp; examine from this point of view the reverse that has so
deeply shocked you.</q>
            <bibl> Staretz Macarius of Optino</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">The wood of this cross that now breaks your back first grew in the
soil of your heart. </q>
            <bibl>Staretz Macarius of Opt[ino]</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">[Holiness is painful as long as it is not shared by all.]</q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(33)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (33) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">When we are incapable of scaling the peaks of virtue, all we have
to do is descend into the ravine of humility. Our humility is our
great intecessor before the face of the Lord. Macarious of OptinoIf
the soul loves and pities the people its prayer is not
interrupted. Staretz SilouanSalvation lies in Christ like
humility. id.  In <hi>Conjectures,</hi> p. 164, Merton mistakenly
ascribes the following extended quotation from Staretz Silouan to a
Staretz Sylvan:He said:&quot;I became steward as an act of obedience
blessed by the Abbot, so I pray better at my task than I prayed at the
Old Rossikon [where he had a solitary hut] where I asked to go for the
sake of interior silence. If the soul loves and pities the people,
prayer is not interrupted. <q direct="unspecified">from <hi>The Undistorted Image</hi>,
biography of Staretz Sylvan (sic), by Archimandrite Sophrony.The
correct reference for this quotation of Staretz Silouan, both in
<hi>Conjectures</hi> and&quot;The Red Diary <q direct="unspecified"> is:Sofrony,
Archimandrite. <hi>The Undistorted Image</hi>. Translated by Rosemary
Edmonds from the Russian. London: The Faith Press, 1958.</q>
               </q>
            </q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(34)" type="Preface">
            <head>X (34) </head>
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <q direct="unspecified"> Not one of us can boast of having acquired humility: our actions,
the whole of our life, prove the contrary. And where there is lack of
humility pride is always present. Where light is wanting, darkness
reigns.</q>
            <bibl>Staretz Macarius of Opt[ino]</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">In the vast sea which is the life of the church the true tradition
of the Spirit flows like a clear pure stream &amp; he who would be in
this stream must renounce argument. When anything of self is
introduced the waters no longer run clear, for God's supreme wisdom
&amp; truth are the opposite of human wisdom &amp; truth. Such
renun-ciation appears intolerable, insane, to the self-willed, but the
man who is not afraid to bcome[sic] a fool has found true life &amp;
true wisdom.</q>
            <bibl>Arch[imandrite] Sophrony</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(35)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (35) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified"> The praying mind does not think, does not reason--it lives. Its
activity does not consist in the manipulation of abstract concepts but
in participating in being. It is concerned with actual existence, an
existence which cannot be included within the narrow framework of
human concepts.</q>
            <bibl>Archimandrite Sophrony</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">The certain sign by which to recognize good from evil is not so
much the end, which may appear to be holy and sublime, as the means
selected to achieve the end.</q>
            <bibl> Archimandrite Sophrony</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(36)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (36) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified"> Blessed are the meek... To understand who the meek are we shall
have to hold fast to Jesus... The meek are those who have truly
humbled themselves, those who have been truly humiliated, those who
have truly fallen from the height to the depths.</q>
            <bibl>K. Barth</bibl>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(37)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (37) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Ultimate meaning and
ultimate wisdom are not found within the world but in God &amp; the
only way to wisdom is through our relationship to God. This
relationship is <hi>awe</hi>. Awe in this sense is more than an
emotion; it is away of understanding. Knowledge is fostered by
curiosity, wisdom [p 52] is fostered by awe.</q>
            <bibl>A. Heschel (Heschel - Between God &amp; Man)</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified"> The secret of every being is the divine care &amp; concern that
are invested in it.</q>
            <bibl>A. Heschel</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">We must be guided by awe to be worthy of faith.</q>
            <bibl>A. Heschel,  id. 53.</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes"> Heschel, Abraham J. <hi>Between God and Man</hi>. Edited by
Fritz A. Rothschild. Toronto: Collier-Macmillan, 1959.</note>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(38)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (38) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">The truth as it is contained in Christian revelation includes the
cognition that it is neither possible to know the truth fully nor to
avoid the error of pretending that he does. It is recognized that
'grace' always remains in partial contradiction to 'nature' &amp; is
not merely its fulfillment. </q>
            <bibl>R. Niebuhr</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes">In the light of this Niebuhr passage, this from Merton's private
journal entry of October 20, 1964:
<q direct="unspecified">At the same time I am beginning to see that <hi>the question of
solitude for me is finally getting to be no longer a question of
desire but of decision</hi>. I still do not know what scope for
decision may be given me, but I do know that I must prepare to face a
serious decision and one about which I had more or less given up
thinking and hoping. It seems to be a real&quot;encounter with the
Word that I must not evade. Yet as in all such things, I am not too
sure just where the encounter is except that <hi>my heart tells me
that in this question of the solitary life there is for me a special
truth to be embraced. A truth which is not capable of fully logical
explanation. A truth which is not rooted in ms own nature or in my own
biography, but is something deeper</hi> and something that may also
cut clean through the whole network of my own recent works, ideas,
writing, experiences and so forth... .  <note anchored="yes"> [emphasis added]</note>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>A Vow of Conversation</hi>. Edited &amp; introduced by Naomi
Burton Stone. New York: Farrar, Straus, Giroux, 1988. p. 88</bibl>
               </q>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(39)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (39) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified"> Individualism understands only a part of man; collectivism
understands man only as a part. Neither advances to the wholeness of
man, to man as a whole. Individualism sees man only in relation to
himself, but collectivism does not see <hi>man</hi> at all, it sees
only&quot;society <q direct="unspecified">.Martin Buber The individual is not an end in
himself &amp; cannot live within himself. Love is the law of his
existence.R. Niebuhr</q>
            </q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(40)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (40) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">The problem of the individual &amp; the community cannot
be solved at all if the height is not achieved where the sovereign
source &amp; end of both individual &amp; communal existence are
discerned; &amp; where the limits are set against the idolatrous
selfworship of both individuals and communities.
<bibl>R. Niebuhr</bibl>
            </q>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(41)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (41) </head>
            <q direct="unspecified">If modern churches were to symbolize their true faith, they would
take the crucifix from their altars and substitute the three little
monkeys who counsel men to&quot;speak no evil, hear no evil, see no
evil.  </q>
            <bibl>R. Niebuhr</bibl>
            <q direct="unspecified">Racial pride is revealed today to be man's primary collective
sin.</q>
            <bibl>R. Niebuhr</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes">Merton incorporates the second Niebuhr quotation in a journal
entry. This is a good example of how Merton's reading became a
springboard for his own expression: Someone has come out with the
theory that racial injustice is the product of
<hi>individualism</hi>. There may be something to it, in the sense
that individualism is a component in the lawlessness and
irresponsibility of a society that has no care whatever to treat other
human beings as if <hi>they</hi> might conceivably have human needs,
and rights. In a sense, even Nazism was a&quot;result of
individualism.   Mass society is indeed made up of individuals who,
left to themselves, know they are zero, and who, added together in a
multitude of zeroes, seem to themselves to acquire reality and
power. But this is the negative individualism of the man who thinks he
establishes himself as real by comparing himself with everything that
is&quot;notI. (When you count up enough things that are not-I, you end
up by discovering that even I is not-I.) But, meanwhile, what is to
blame is not individualism but collectivism. Reinhold Niebuhr says
rightly:&quot;Racial pride is revealed today as man's
primary<hi>collective</hi> sin.<hi>Conjectures</hi>, p. 56.</note>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X(42)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X (42)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified"> On perd toujours quelque chose apres de Dieu lorsqu'on veut trop
justifier aupr'es des hommes.</q>
            <bibl> Mabillon</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes">Something is always lost in the sight of God when we want to justify
too much in the sight of men</note>
            <q direct="unspecified">Ceux[-]la seuls ont puissamment agi qui, au gout de l'eternel et de
la reflexion solitaire, ont joint quelque passion apostolique, chez
qui la quete du Vraia ete soutenue sans cesse par le desir d'aider, de
reformer les hommes, et qui ntont accepte la retraite que pour
concentrer leur flamme et vue d'un rayonnement plus lumineux et plus
ardent.</q>
            <bibl>M. Festugiere</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes">[Only they have acted with power who, to their penchant for the
eternal and for solitary reflection, have added some form of apostolic
passion: only those in whome the quest for the True has incessantly
been sustained by a desire to aid and reform men, and who have
consented to withdraw from the world only in order to concentrate
their flame the more, in view of a more luminous and more ardent
radiance.]</note>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="X (43)" type="Preface">
            <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
            <head>X(43)</head>
            <q direct="unspecified">Qui enim a nullis refraenat licitis vicinus est illictis.</q>
            <bibl> (Aug. de Ut. Jejunii 5.)</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes">[Whoever does not refrain from some licit things is close to
(engaging in) illicit ones.]</note>
            <q direct="unspecified">(Nov. 1964) Locutus est mihi (Dominus) et dixit[:]Ingredere
et includere in mediodomus tuae.</q>
            <bibl>Ezech 3:24</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes">[(The Lord)
spoke to me and said: Go in and shut thyself up in the midst of thy
house.</note>
            <q direct="unspecified">To the extent that each man believes the end concerning future blessings &amp; despises human glory &amp; pleasures, he will have couresponding power to control his
thoughts &amp; to be more at peace than a man who loves pleasures.</q>
            <bibl>St. Mark The Ascetic (Philokalia )</bibl>
            <note anchored="yes">]This and all subsequent translation of scriptural quotation
follows the Douay version of the Latin Vulgate text.In November, 1964,
Merton participates in an important meeting of abbots and novice
masters, holds a retreat for for[sic] the Fellowship of
Reconcilliation (FOR), and receives many diverse visitors. See Michael
Mott, <hi>The Seven Mountains of Thomas Merton.</hi>
pp. 405-406.</note>
            <div1 n="X(44)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (44) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Ut totis viribus quieti mentis studeas, sine qua nulli licet
callidi hostis insidias circumspicere.St. Anselm, Ep. 37
(S___III. 147)Sed vide ne hostes derideant abbata tua, ne illis
serviant otia tua, ne illis vaces, qui vacare Deodebueras .Gilbert of
HoylandIn Cant. 11.5. PL 184, 60.  <note anchored="yes">[With all your faculties you
ought to be intent on peace of mind, for without it no one can take
heed of the traps set for him by the cunning enemy.][But see to it
that (your) enemies do not make a mockery of your sabbaths, lest your
inactivity be of service to them, lest your leisure be for them when
it ought to have been for God.]</note>
               </q>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(45)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (45)</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>Texts for an Office of Hermits</hi>
               </head>
               <q direct="unspecified">Levate in caelum oculos vestros et videte sub terra deorsum; quia
caeli sicut fumus liquescent et terra sicut vestimentum atteretur, et
habitatores eius sicut haec interibunt, salus autem mea in sempiternum
erit et justitia mea non deficiet.</q>
               <bibl>Isa. 51:6</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[Lift up your eyes to heaven, and look down to the earth
beneath: for the heavens shall vanish like smoke, and the earth shall
be worn away like a garment, and the inhabitants thereof shall perish
in like manner: but my salvation shall be forever, and my justice
shall not fail.]</note>
               <q direct="unspecified">Posui verba mea in ore tuo et in umbra manus meae protexi te, ut
plantes caelos et fundes ierram et dicas ad Sion: populus meus es
tu.</q>
               <bibl>Isa 51:16</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[I have put my words in thy mouth, and have protected thee in
the shadow of my hand, that thou mightest plant the heavens, and found
the earth: and mightest say to Sion: Thou art my people.]* Merton is
inconsistent in his use of consonantal&quot;in Latin: sometimes he
retains the classical&quot; and sometimes he uses the medieval&quot;</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(46)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (46)</head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Non in tumultu exibitis nec in fuga properabitis, praecedet enim
vos Dominus et congregabit vos Deus Israel.</q>
               <bibl> Isa. 52:</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[You shall not go out in a tumult, neither shall you make haste
by flight: for the Lord will go before you, and the God of Israel will
gather you together.]</note>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Sweep your cell clean of everything superfluous for this will lead
you to abstinence, however unwillingly. Scarcity of all things teaches
a man to be abstinent.</q>
               <bibl>Isaac of Neneveh.  (Kadloubovsky,
E. and Palmer, G.E.H., translators. <hi>Early Fathers from the
Philokalia</hi>. London: Faber and Faber Limited, 1954  p 235)</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">If you do not strive you will not find &amp; if you do not
knock at he door with ardor &amp; constantly keep vigil before it, you
will not be heard. EFP. 235</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(47)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (47) </head>
               <bibl>Sermon from Isaac of N.[ineveh]</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">Is there any need
to say anything about men engaged in spiritual endeavor, strangers to
the world, &amp; about hermits? They have made the wilderness a city
&amp; transformed it into the home &amp; the abode of the angels. For
the righteousness of their life the angels always come to them &amp;
as warriors of the same King they have often fought side by side. All
their life have they loved the wilderness &amp; from love of God had
their dwelling in the mountains, caves &amp; precipices of the
earth. Since they have abandoned the earthly &amp; conceived of love
for the heavenly, imitating the angels, the* text continues on X
(48).</q>
               <note anchored="yes"> In a journal entry for January 11, 1965 Merton notes
Isaac of Nineveh as a favorite:  A little Nietzsche is stimulating, no
doubt, but what I really like to read is Isaac of Neneveh in the
hermitage or Zen Masters in the fields.  <hi>A Vow of
Conversation</hi>, p. 133.</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(48)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (48)  </head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> holy angels themselves have deemed it right not to conceal from
them their countenance &amp; have fulfilled their every wish, giving
them all possible help. </q>
               <bibl>EFP. p 237.</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">(Isaac. contd) He is a monk who stays outside the world &amp; is
ever praying to God so that he may gain future blesshings. A monk's
wealth is the comfort he finds in mourning, &amp; the joy of faith
which shines in the secret places of his
mind.</q>
               <bibl>EFP. 240</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Blessed are those who from love of God have girded their loins
with unquestioningsimplicity for this sea of suffering &amp; who donot
turn back.</q>
               <bibl>EFP 244</bibl>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(49)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (49) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> When hope embarks on this passage it crosses the sea with its
first ardour, having no care at all for the body nor deliberating in
itself as to whether or no its labour begun will in any wise
succeed.</q>
               <bibl>(Isaac. EFP. 244)</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">God commands that we should undertake the work with readiness to
die for the sake of pleasing Him, &amp; He promises to crown the
faithful laborer with thehonour of martyrdom.</q>
               <bibl>EFP. 246</bibl>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(50)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (50) </head>
               <head>Office of hermits</head>
               <q direct="unspecified">Haec dicit Dominus: quomodo si inveniatur granum in botro et
dicatur: ne dissipes illud quoniam benedictio est; Sic faciam propter
servos meos ut non disperdam totum.</q>
               <bibl>Isa. 65:8</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[Thus saith the Lord: As if a grain be found in a cluster, and
it be said: Destroy it not, because it is a blessing: so will I do for
the sake of my servants, that I may not destroy the whole.] </note>
               <q direct="unspecified">Ad quem autem respiciam nisi ad pauperculum et contritum spiritu
et trementem sermones meos.</q>
               <bibl>Isa. 66:2</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes"> [But to whom shall I look but to him that is poor and little,
and of a contrite spirit, and that trembleth at my words?] </note>
               <q direct="unspecified">Intrans in domum meam conquiescam cum sapientia: non enim habet
amaritudinem conversatio illius, nec taedium convictus illius, sed
laetitiam et gaudium.</q>
               <bibl>Sap 8:16 (Jan 31, 1965) *</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[When I go into my house, I shall repose myself with wisdom: for her
conversation hath no bitterness, nor her company any tediousness, but
joy and gladness.]* See note on following page.
<hi>Addendum</hi>Merton's selection of texts under the
title,&quot;Office of Hermits,  begins in this notebook after
November, 1964 and continues through and beyond his fiftieth birthday,
January 31, 1965. Since there were many indications he would soon be
allowed to live in the hermitage permanently, the annual retreat of
January 18  26 was especially important. Merton's&quot;Office for
Hermits  may well have been conceived and begun during this annual
retreat. [See Mott, pp. 410-412 for events preceding Merton's
birthday.]How much of Merton's&quot;office  was gathered on his
birthday is impossible to accurately gage. Was it more than page 50?
Was it limited only to the quotation of Sap 8:16 marked by Merton's
marginalia which signals its importance? Merton's birth date at this
place may well have been added later by him, though this does not
lessen the significance of either the entire page or the one
passage.In any case, the passages of Merton's&quot;office  can be
allowed to&quot;sing  with journal entries marked as written on the
vigil of his birthday and the anniversary itself (Jan. 3031, 1965):
What I find most in my whole life is illusion, wanting to be something
of which I have formed a concept. I hope I will get free of all that
now, because that is going to be the struggle and yet I have to be
something that I ought to be. I have to meet a certain demand for
order and inner light and tranquillity, God's demand, that is, that I
remove obstacles to His giving me all these. Snow, silence, the
talking fire, the watch on the table, sorrow. What would be the use of
going over all this? I will just get cleaned up (my hands are dirty)
and say the Psalms of my birthday:'Yet you drew me out of the womb
you entrusted me to my mother's breast placed on your lap from my
birth from my mother's womb you have been my God'&quot; (Jan 30) I can
imagine no greater cause for gratitude on my fiftieth birthday than:
that, on it, I woke up in a hermitage. Fierce cold all night,
... . Inside the house, it almost froze, though embers still glowed
under the ashes in the fireplace. The cold woke meup at one point, but
I adjusted the blankets and went back to sleep.  What more do I seek
than this silence, this simplicity, this&quot;living together with
wisdom ? For me, there is nothing else... [emphasis added] (Jan 31)A
<hi>Vow of Conversation</hi>, pp. 141-142.</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(51)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (51)</head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> The Lord suffers all human weaknesses but abhors a man who is
always complaining, &amp; does not leave him without a lesson. </q>
               <bibl>Isaac of N. EFP. p. 269</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">A man who remembering God respects every man, by a
sudden move-ment of God's hand himself receives help from every man.</q>
               <bibl> id.</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">Praecordia fatui quasi rota carri, et quasi axis versatilis
cogitatus illius.</q>
               <bibl> Eccli. [Ecclesiasticus] 33:5 </bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[The heart of a fool is as a wheel of a cart, and his thoughts
are like a rolling axletree.]</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(52)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (52) </head>
               <head>(office )</head>
               <q direct="unspecified">A cella quippe in caelum saepe
ascenditur; vix autem aut numquam a cella in infernum descenditur,
nisi cogitando de pravis inferni. Moriens autem vix umquam aliquis a
cella in infernum descendit, quia vix umquam aliquis nisi caelo
praedestinatus in ea usque ad mortem persistit: quoniam filium gratiae
cella tanquam fructum ventris sui foret [feret?].</q>
               <note anchored="yes">[From the
cell (<hi>cella</hi>) one can often go up to heaven (<hi>caelum</hi>);
but hardly ever or never does one go from the cell down to hell,
except by dwelling on the depraved things of hell. At the moment of
death, hardly ever does anyone go down from the cell to hell, because
hardly ever does anyone persevere in it until death unless he is
predestined for heaven: because the cell bears[?] a son of grace like
the fruit of its womb.]</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(53)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (53) </head>
               <head>office</head>
               <q direct="unspecified">Haec dicit Dns exercituum: Ponite corda vestra super vias
vestras. Seminastis multum et intulistis parum, comedistis et non
estis satiati, bibistis et non estis inebriati, operuistis vos et non
estis calefacti, et qui mercedes congreagavist misit eas in sacculum
pertusum. </q>
               <bibl>Aggaeus 1:5-6</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[Thus saith the Lord of Hosts: Set your hearts to consider your
ways. You have sowed much, and brought in little: you have eaten, but
have not been sated: you have drunk, but have not been inebriated: you
have clothed yourselves, but have not been warmed: and he that hath
earned wages, put them into a bag with holes.]</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(54)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (54)</head>
               <head>office</head>
               <q direct="unspecified">Ne despicias narrationem presbyterorum sapientium, et in
proverbiis eorum conversare; ab ipsis enim disces sapientiam et
doctrinam intellectus et servire magnatis sine querela. Non te
praetereat narratio seniorum, ipsi enim didicerunt a patribus suis;
quoniam ab ipsis disces intellectum et in tempore necessitatis dare
responsum.</q>
               <bibl>Ecclus. VIII, 9-12</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[Despise not the discourse of them that are ancient and wise,
but acquaint thyself with their proverbs. For of them thou shalt learn
wisdom, and instruction of understanding, and to serve great men
without quarrel. Let not the discourse of the ancients escape thee,
for they have learned of their fathers: for of them thou shalt learn
understanding, and to given an answer in time of need.]</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(55)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (55) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified">
                  <lg>
                     <l>No Thing you love must be</l>
                     <l>And from<hi>Thing</hi>you must flee.</l>
                     <l>You must stand alone</l>
                     <l>with no man make your home.</l>
                     <l> From all striving cease, </l>
                     <l>From all beings find release.</l>
                     <l> Loose what you captive find</l>
                     <l> And what is free fast bind.</l>
                     <l> Bring comfort to the sick</l>
                     <l> For yourself nothing seek.</l>
                     <l> Drink from the spring of bitterness. </l>
                     <l>To light love's fire bring</l>
                     <l>Fuel of goodness.</l>
                     <l> So will your dwelling</l>
                     <l> Be wilderness.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <bibl>Mccha, A. of Mazt.</bibl>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(56)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (56) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified">O Domina et Mater misericordiae quae mundo edidisti Salvatorem,
oratrix pro me dignanter assiste. Ad tuum gloriosissimum et singulare
praesidium confugio, et tu, piissima, meis precibus aures tuae
pietatis inclina. Vehementer expavesco ne vita mea tuo dis-pliceat
filio, et illo [sic] deprecor ut sicut per te se mundo mani-festavit,
propter te, quaeso, absque dilatione miseratur mei. Qui vivit et
regnat.(St. Odo) <note anchored="yes">[O Lady and Mother of mercy who gave the world
the Savior, consent to be my intercessor. I flee to your most gracious
and singular protection, and you, O most faithful one, incline the
ears of your fidelity to my prayers. I strongly fear that my life may
not be pleasing to your son, and I entreat him that, just as he
manifested himself to the world through you, so too, I beg, may he
have pity on me without delay for your sake. Who lives and
reigns.]</note>
               </q>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(57)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (57) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified">Fili in mansuetudine serva animam tuam et da illi honorem secundum
meritum tuum.</q>
               <note anchored="yes">[My son, keep thy soul in meekness, and give it
honor according to its desert.]</note>
               <bibl>Eccli. 10:31</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">(Stability in solitude.) Sta in testamento
tuo et in illo colloquere, et in opere mandatorum tuorum veterasce. Ne
manseris in operibus peccatorum, <hi>confide autem</hi> 
                  <hi>in Deo et
in mane in loco tuo</hi>.</q>
               <bibl>Eccli. 11:2122</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes"> [Be steadfast in thy covenant, and be
conversant therein, and grow old in the work of thy
commandments. Abide not in the works of sinners, <hi>but trust in God
and stay in thy place</hi>.]</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(58)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (58)</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>office</hi>
               </head>
               <bibl>Prayer of Fulbert of Chartres (excerpt)</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Impetra
michi sancta Virgo Maria spatium et locum penitentiae ut non sinar in
vacuum ducere dies huic mortali vitae concessos. Sancta Dei Genitrix
perpetua Virgo Maria, intercede pro me, ut omnipotens Deus aperire
dignetur michi voluntatem suam, qualiter anima mea possit slava
fieri. Dancta Dei Genitrix perpetua Virgo Maria, impetra michi
compunctionis lacrimas, ut innumerabilia peccata mea incessanter
defleam, ut sicut fuit michi dulce peccare ita michi sit dulce
paenitere et lugere, non solum propria sed et aliena commissa.
<note anchored="yes">[O Holy Virgin Mary, obtain for me a space and a place of
repentence that I may not be allowed to spend vainly the days granted
to this mortal life. Holy Mother of God, ever Virgin Mary, obtain for
me the tears of compunction that I may weep incessantly for my
numberless sins, so that, just as sinning was sweet to me, so too I
may find it sweet to do penance and mourn, not only for my own sins
but also for those committed by others.]</note>
               </q>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(59)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (59) </head>
               <bibl>From Psalter of Robert of Molesme</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">O intemerata et in
aeternum benedicta, specialis et incomparabilis Dei Genitrix Virgo
Maria, gratissimum Dei templum, Spiritus Sancti sacrarium, ianua
caelorum, per quam post Deum totus vivit orbis terrarum, inclina aures
tuae sanctae virginalis humilitatis et pietatis indignis
supplicationibus meis, et esto michi miserrimo peccatori pia et
propitia in omnibus auxiliatrix.  <note anchored="yes">[O Mother of God, Virgin Mary,
fearless and forever blessed, singular and incomparable, most pleasing
temple of God, tabernacle of the Holy Spirit, gate of heaven, through
whom--after God--all on earth have their life: incline the ears of
your holy virginal humility and fidelity to my unworthy prayers, and
in all things be for me, a most wretched sinner, a faithful and
well-disposed helper.]</note>
               </q>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(60)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (60)</head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Fugite de medio Babylonis et salvetunusquisque animam suam;
nolitetacere super iniquitatem eius,quoniam tempus ultionis est
aDomino, vicissitudinem ipse retribuetei. Calix aureus Babylon in
manuDomini inebrians omnem terram;de vino eius biberunt gentes etido
commotae sunt. Subito ceciditBabylon et contrita est. Ulutatesuper
eam; tol[l]ite resinam addolorem eius si forte sanetur.Curavimus
Babylonem et non estsanata, derelinquamus eam et eamusunusquisque in
terram suam, quoniampervenit usque ad caelos judicium eius,et elevatum
est usque ad numbes.</q>
               <bibl>Jerem. 51. [69]</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">[Flee yet from the midst of Babylon, and let every one save his
own life: be not silent upon her iniquity: for it is the time of
revenge from the Lord, he will render unto her what she hath
deserved. Babylon hath been a golden cup in the hand of the Lord, that
made all the earth drunk: the nations have drunk of her wine, and
therefore they have staggered. Babylon is suddenly fallen, and
destroyed: howl for her, take balm for her pain, if so she may be
healed. We would have cured Babylon, but she is not healed: let us
forsake her, and let us go every man to his own land: because her
judgment hath reached even to the heavens, and is lifted up to the
clouds.]</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(61)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (61)</head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Cur per multa vagaris homuncio, quaerendo bona animae tuae et
corporis tui? Ama unum bonum in quo sunt omnia bona, et
sufficit.Anselm. Proslogion XXV </q>
               <note anchored="yes">[Why, little man, do you run
from one thing to another, searching for the goods of your soul and of
your body? Love the one good in which are all goods, and that will
suffice.]</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(62)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (62) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Deficient pueri et laborabunt, et iuvenes in infirmitate cadent;
qui autem sperant in Domino mutabunt fortitudinem, adsument pennas
sicut aquilae, current et non laborabunt, ambulabunt et non deficient.</q>
               <note anchored="yes">[Youths shall faint and labor, and young men shall fall by
infirmity. But they that hope in the Lord shall renew their strength,
they shall take wings as eagles, they shall run and not be weary, they
shall walk and not faint.][And I will wait for the Lord, who hath hid
his face from the house of Jacob, and I will look for him.]</note>
               <bibl> Isa. 40:30-31</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">Et exspectabo Dominum qui abscondit faciem suam a domo Jacob et
praestolabor eum.</q>
               <note anchored="yes">[And I will wait for the Lord, who hath hid
his face from the house of Jacob, and I will look for
him.]</note>
               <bibl>Isa. 8:17</bibl>
               <note anchored="yes">That Isaias be included in the&quot;office of hermits is not
accidental. Isaias as an important source for Merton in understanding
his monastic and hermit aspirations has had a long history in Merton's
writing. In 1951 Merton writes:&quot;Do you suppose I have a spiritual
life? I have none, I am indigence, I am silence, I am poverty, I am
solitude, for I have renounced spirituality to find God, and He it is
Who preachesloud in the depths of my indigence, saying:&quot;I will
pourout my spirit upon thy children and they shall spring up among the
herbs as willows beside the running waters (Isaias, 55:3-4).&quot;The
children of thy barrenness shall say in thy ears: The place is too
strait for me, make me room to dwell in (Isaias, 49:20). I die of love
for you, Compassion: I take you for my Lady, as Francis married
poverty I marry you, the Queen of hermits and the Mother of the
poor.<hi>The Sign of Jonas.</hi> New York: Image Books edition,
1956. pp. 323-324.</note>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(63)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (63) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> (Christus) luctatus est eum et vicit: erat enim homo pro patribus
certans, et per obedientiam, inobedientiam persolvens: alligavit enim
fortem, et solvit infirmos, et salutem donavit plasmati suo, destruens
peccatum. Est enim piissimus et misericors Dominus et amans humanum
genus.  <note anchored="yes">[(Christ) laid hold of him and defeated him: for he was
a man combatting for his ancestors, and undoing (their) disobedience
by (his) obedience: he fettered the strong one and he released the
weak, and he gave salvation to his creation, destroying sin. Thus, he
is a most faithful and merciful Lord, one who loves the human
race.]</note>
               </q>
               <bibl>St. Irenaeus Adv. III.xix.5  (_____
p. 47n.</bibl>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(64)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (64) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Insuper et sabbata mea dedi eis ut essent signum inter me et eos
et scirent quia ego Dominus sanctificans eos.  <note anchored="yes">[Moreover I gave
them also my sabbaths to be a sign between me and them: and that they
might know that I am the Lord that sanctify
them.]</note>
               </q>
               <bibl>Ezech. XX. 12</bibl>
               <q direct="unspecified">Dixi autem ad filios eorum in solitudine: In praeceptis patrum
vestrorum nolite incedere, ne judicia eorum custodiatis, nec in idolis
eorum polluamini. Ego Dominus Deus vester, in praeceptis meis
ambulate, judicia mea custodite et facite eas et sabbata mea
sanctificate ut sint signum inter me et vos et sciatis quia ego sum
Dominus Deus vester.  <note anchored="yes"> [And I said to their children in the
wilderness: Walk not in the statutes of your fathers, and observe not
their judgments, nor be ye defiled with their idols: I am the Lord
your God: walk ye in my statutes and observe my judgments, and do
them. And sanctify my sabbaths, that they may be a sign between me and
you: and that you may know that I am the Lord your
God.]</note>
               </q>
               <bibl>Ezech. XX. 18-20</bibl>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(65)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (65) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified"> Inter sanctum et profanum non habuerunt distantiam et inter
pollutum et mundum non intellexerunt et a sabbatis meis averterunt
oculos meos et conqui-nabar in medio eorum.... Et quaesivi de eis
virum qui interponeret sepem et staret oppositus contra me pro terra
ne dissiparem eam, et non inveni.  <note anchored="yes">[They have put no difference
between holy and profane nor have distinguished between the polluted
and the clean and they have turned away their eyes from my sabbaths
and I was profaned in the midst of them.... And I sought among them
for a man that might set up a hedge and stand in the gap before me in
favor of the land, that I might not destroy it: and I found
none.]</note>
               </q>
               <bibl>Ezech. XXII. [26b, 30]</bibl>
            </div1>
            <div1 n="X(66)" type="Preface">
               <docAuthor>Merton, Thomas.  RED DIARY.  </docAuthor>
               <head>X (66) </head>
               <q direct="unspecified">Ephraim pascit ventum et sequitur aestum tota die. Mendacium et
vastitatem multiplicat... Et tu ad Deum tuum converteris,
misericordiam et judicium custodi et spera in Deo tuo semper.
<note anchored="yes">[in standard editions, verses are 1 and 6.]</note>
                  <note anchored="yes">&lt;[Ephraim feedeth on the wind and followeth the heat all the day
long. He multiplies lies and desolation... Therefore turn thou to thy
God: keep mercy and judgment and hope in thy God always.]</note>
               </q>
               <bibl>Osee. 12:2,7.</bibl>
            </div1>
            <back/>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>